All right. So, today we're going to talk
about a little bit about HTML and
starting your first web page. So, what
we're going to want to do is just like I
said in the last video, is we want
everything in this course, we want to be
working in a folder. So, the very first
thing we want to do is open a folder.
So, come over here and click on these uh
this explorer tab and then we're going
to click open folder. In the last video,
I created um a folder on my desktop
called first website. And I'm going to
open that. Or if you are following
along, you can create you're welcome to
create your own website, your own folder
here. Um but I'm just going to use this
first website folder that I made in the
last video. So I'm going to click open.
And now that folder is open. So over
here on the lefth hand panel, you can
see that this folder doesn't have any
folders or files in it at all. We're
going to start by making a first our
first file. Typically, when you make
your first HTML file, you'll name it
index.html because that is where um
computers will go automatically when
they're looking for the homepage of your
website. They'll look for index.html.
So, I'm going to create index.html. The
way I do that is this little icon here
that looks like a piece of paper with
the top corner folded down that says new
file. I'm going to click on that and I'm
going to type in index.html.
Importantly, you do not want to include
spaces in this file name. So, I'm going
to hit enter. And you can tell that I
have the right thing because it'll have
these two carrot signs. And that is how
you know that it's an HTML file. Also,
down at the bottom, it says that the
type of language we're writing in is
HTML.
If you don't see that, make sure you
typed HTML as lowercase. Also, make sure
you typed HTML with no spaces. Um, and
that should handle the language. If that
doesn't happen, you can come down here
at the bottom and you can click HTML and
you can click change it from auto detect
and then you can scroll down and you can
tell it that you want it to be HTML. So
you can manually set which language
you're using, but if you put HTML,
Visual Studio Code is smart enough that
it should be able to figure out what
type of language you're using.
HTML is a coding
language that um structures a website.
It's composed of opening tags and
closing tags. Any website you see on the
internet is composed of HTML.
So the typical format for HTML is you
have an opening HTML tag and a closing
HTML tag. And that tells the computer,
hey, this is going to be a web page.
Inside of that HTML, you have two more
tags. So you'll have a head tag,
an opening and a closing one, and then
you'll have a body tag. And if you don't
type the carrots and you just hit tab,
it will autocomplete and create the
closing tag for you. And that'll save
you from having to type the carrot sign
all the time because for me, it's in an
awkward spot on the keyboard. So
typically an HTML page will have an HTML
tag that contains everything. Inside of
that HTML tag, it'll have a head tag and
inside of that it will have a body tag.
The body is most most of what you see on
a web page. The head tag is helpful for
search engines as they're looking for
your website. So, a lot of times you'll
put a lot of information in the head tag
that will help your website be found.
The body tag is where you'll put a lot
of the stuff that will show up on the
page for your users.
Now, if you're like me, you don't like
typing if you don't have to. So, there
is a shortcut for all of this. So rather
than just typing out everything that I
just typed out here, you can type HTML
colon 5 and hit tab and that'll put in
all of the boilerplate code to build
your first HTML page. Or you can type
exclamation mark and hit enter and that
will type out all of the code. The
exclamation mark is what I commonly use
to put in all of my boilerplate HTML
code. So I want you to see this live.
And one thing I want to point out is
there's a little white dot up here next
to our tab. That means that our file
hasn't been saved. If you're ever
writing code and you're wondering why
your website's not updating to reflect
your changes, check to make sure that
you've saved it. There are a couple ways
you could do this, but I prefer the
keyboard shortcut. So, you can hit
commands on a Mac or control S on a
Windows and that will save it. But if
you don't like keyboard shortcuts, um
you can come up here to the top and hit
file and then hit save. And that will
save your file.
So I'm going to hit this little go live
button. And that will pop open
a website. And there's nothing on it.
And that's exactly what we're hoping to
see. We didn't want to see anything on
this website um because we haven't
written any HTML to show anything. All
we've written is the boilerplate code.
So, let's go make it actually do
something. So, change tabs back over to
Visual Studio. And in Visual Studio,
let's type inside of the body tags,
we're going to say hello world because
this is a programming course. Wouldn't
be a programming course if we didn't
start with hello world. So, we'll save
that because we're running live server.
As soon as we save a change here, that's
when we click this go live down at the
bottom. As soon as we save a change on
our index.html file, it updates on our
website. And so now we can see that our
website has hello world. If we mouse
over the lefth hand tab, we can see that
we have one tab and that tab is called
document. It's going to look a little
different in if you're on Google Chrome.
Um I'm in Safari right now. Um maybe we
don't want our tab to say document.
Maybe we want it to say something else.
So we'll come back over to our Visual
Studio Code. This isn't information
that's displayed on the page. It's
information about the page. So, we're
going to look in the head tag. And right
here in title, we can see that it says
document. Let's change that to say our
first website. So, I'm going to type um
my first website and hit command S to
save my changes. You'll notice the white
dot disappeared. If we tab back over, we
can see that our website still looks the
same. It still says hello world. But now
if we look at our tabs,
we can see that the tab is labeled my
first website. And so hopefully that
gets you a little bit of an orientation
to HTML. Um,
we're only going to go into as much
depth in HTML as you need to understand
JavaScript because this is primarily a
JavaScript course. Um, and maybe one day
in the future I'll make an HTML course,
but for now we're just going to focus on
JavaScript. So, thank you for watching
and have a good